Else von Richthofen Collection MS008
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Else von Richthofen Collection
1900 -- 1915
1898 -- 1984
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Green, Martin
Jaffe-Richthofen, Else
MS008
1.25 Linear Feet
190 Digital Object(s)
9.5 Megabytes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Letters and correspondence, and Research material.
Custodial History
Martin Green collected these letters from Else von Richthofen. After completing the two books, Professor Green donated the original letters and his research material to Tufts University.
Scope and Contents
In the course of writing his two books, "The von Richthofen Sisters" (1974), and "The Mountain of Truth" (1986), Tufts University professor Martin Green collected original letters given to him by Else von Richthofen, and secondary material relating to his work studying the Ascona movement.
The principals in the correspondence are Else von Richthofen-Jaffe and Frieda Schloffer-Gross. Else von Richthofen-Jaffe was the sister of Frieda Weekley, wife of the British novelist D.H. Lawrence. Else was born in Metz in 1874 and married Edgar Jaffe, an economist of Max Weber's circle in Heidelberg.
Frieda Schloffer-Gross was the wife of the famous psychoanalyst Otto Gross. She was at one time a student of Sigmund Freud, but later became his adversary. Else, Frieda, Otto Gross, and a number of others mentioned in the letters were part of a larger movement in early twentieth-century Europe that advocated a return to "nature." They participated in the creation of what is now known as "modern" thought and culture.
Biographical / Historical
Elisabeth Helene Amalie Sophie Freiin (Baroness) von Richthofen (also known as Else Jaffé) was born in Château-Salins, France on October 8, 1874. Her parents were Friedrich Ernst Emil Ludwig Freiherr von Richthofen (1844-1915), an engineer in the German army, and Anna Elise Lydia Marquier (1852-1930).
Although Else von Richthofen first worked as a teacher, she earned her doctorate in economics from Heidelberg University in 1901 and started work as a labor inspector in Karlsruhe. She married Edgar Jaffé (1865-1921), a well-known economist and entrepreneur, in 1902. After Jaffé bought the journal Archiv für Sozialwissenschaft und Sozialpolitik, his former professor, Max Weber, became one of its editors. With Jaffé, Else had three children, Friedel (born 1903), Marianne (born 1905) and Hans (born 1909).
Else became acquainted with intellectuals and authors, including the psychoanalyst Otto Gross (with whom she had a fourth child, Peter), the writer Fanny zu Reventlow, and others. She also had affairs with her former professor Max Weber and his brother Alfred Weber with whom she later lived for several years after her husband died.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Green, Martin; von Richthofen, Else; Gross, Otto; Faculty research
- Letters and correspondence, 1898 -- 1947; 1900 -- 1915; MS008.001; 0.75 Linear Feet; 190 Digital Object(s) Each transcript has two versions - one in PDF and the other in MS Word.; 9.5 Megabytes
  Scope and Contents
  Original letters and correspondence given to Martin Green by Else von Richthofen-Jaffe. Most have been written between 1900 and 1915. The bulk of the material is letters to Else from Frieda Schloffer-Gross. These letters are item-level cataloged, and have summaries in English. Some letters, principally from Otto Gross also have English summaries. Other letters, from Otto Gross and others, have not been summarized. The letters were not in order when they were received by Professor Green. An attempt has been made to reconstruct the original order of the letters, but some documents are clearly fragments of longer letters and their original order has been lost. There are typescripts (in German) of 45 of the letters (items 45-90) to Else von Richthofen.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged numerically by Professor Green's numbering system.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00001; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She tells about a recent move to a new place. She mentions Hickson, who is in the process of writing a book. Seems to be in a melancholic and confused mood about herself and the future.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer?] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00002; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Discusses her relationship with Hickson whom she is very fond of and whose character she admires. Expresses concern that Else will throw herself completely into her work and will neglect "the duties of love" which she calls the "crown of feminine life." Expects the future to be difficult for herself.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00003; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda expresses her surprise and joy about Else receiving her doctorate after six semesters.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00004; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She seems depressed and full of melancholy. Refers to problems with her leg which her physicians attribute to her bad nerves. She takes arsenic and receives electro-shock therapy for her neurosis. Considers Else as her only trusted friend. She feels her neurosis is related to her hysterical mother.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00005; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    After she recuperated in Abbazia her emotional and physical suffering has returned. Hickson seems to hold back-offers no commitment, nothing tangible which is distressing her.
  - ? to ?, 1900; MS008.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    Fragment. Mentions expected arrival of a new child-a sibling for Gerti. Arnold is the father. The date is written in a different writing on back of the letter.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer?] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00007; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She talks about the upcoming Christmas holidays which everyone expects to celebrate with family and friends. It is not clear if the letter is a fragment.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.001.00008; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    This is a response to a letter from Else. She alludes to someone who is not necessarily an angel. Post card.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00009; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    [Frieda] seems happy and jealous about a serious relationship Else is having and encourages her to get married. She is nostalgic about the "blossoms of love" that existed between them. Letter is fragment.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00010; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda refers to an event in Else's life which she finds hard to believe [possibly the dissolution of a relationship with a man]. Frieda states her undying love and support for Else and how she was not really able to share in Else's previous happiness.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00011; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda is inquiring on behalf of a friend who seperated from her husband about living arrangements for single women who plan to study in Karlsruhe. Post card.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00012; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She is very philosophical about the ups and downs of life. She is positive about the idea of marriage.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00013; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She makes plans for a visit with Else. She mentions a man, whom she describes as an idealist and who does not fit the times and the Graz social scene. She met him during a musical gathering-she herself enjoys playing the piano. Letter is a fragment.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00014; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She is clarifying her travel plans for visiting Else. She declares her need for an object of "active affection" and asks Else if she wanted to be it.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00015; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She is worn out from the many obligations, especially towards other people and is looking forward to her visit with Else.
  - refers to herself as the Blonde woman [Frieda Gross] to Bethel (Else von Richtofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00016; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda expresses her gratitude for Else's understanding. She reports on a visit in Stuttgart with a wealthy family, where she observed how the young wife was losing her individuality under the influence of her husband. Tells about her experience at the "Institution Hessing" for crippled people. Frieda escorted Aunt Sofie to this place.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00017; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    [Frieda] describes her experience at the "Institute Hessing" where she is staying as Aunt Sofie's companion. She is observing the suffering of the crippled people who are seeking a cure with the help of Hessing's modern therapeutic exercise equipment. Hessing, the owner of the clinic, is making sexual advances to most women patients. The patients are from all over the world. Letter is a fragment.
  - refers to herself as your women [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richtofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00018; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    [Frieda] considers Aunt Sofie's decision to interrupt her "cure", her stay at the rehabilitation clinic as a mistake and blames "him" [possibly Aunt Sofie's husband] for this decision.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00019; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Reports from a sailing vacation in the South where she enjoys the beauty of nature in the company of her father. She dreads the return to Graz [her home] and wishes to work there with old and sick people and children.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00020; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Friedel is full of amiration for Else doing her lecture tour. Feels her own life is trivial-has desire to experience life. She feels the same attachment to Else and likens it to the feeling for a husband.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901; MS008.001.001.00021; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    She tells of the love and tender feelings she has for Else. Expresses disappointment about not receiving a Christmas card from Hickson. She talks of her "intensive" correspondence with Smith, a young American who is crippled and who seems to develop an affection for her. Letter is a fragment.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00022; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Friedel states her personal impressions and feelings about Hermann who seems to be in the process of becoming a professor. She finds her nursing classes very interesting.
  - Sofie [Riehl, Frieda Gross' Aunt] to Elisabeth [Else von Richtofen ?], 1902; MS008.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
    Sofie tells about her enjoyable Spring vacation in Eisnach. Contemplates Friedel's [Frieda Gross] future in the nursing field. Emphasizes Friedel's love for mankind. Feels a visit to berlin where social efforts are being implemented would be of interest. Urges Elisabeth to read the true idealism in "Memoirs of a Revolutionary" by Krapotkin.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00024; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Friedel asks Bethel about her opinion of a man who is involved in a love triangle and who is dishonest about it towards one of the women. This man feels the need to conquer her [Frieda Gross] even though she is unsure about her feelings and the entire situation.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1901 -- 1902; MS008.001.001.00025; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Friedel relates a story about a couple who is deeply in love, but he does not want to marry her because of the age difference. Both are suffering terribly and Friedel finds the situation crazy. Friedel is happiest in the company of women and does not think she will get married. She wants to do social work.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00026; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Friedel [Frieda Gross] expresses her happiness about Else's engagement. States that the beauty of life can only be enjoyed as a couple. Tells of her own wonderful relationship with Otto Gross which just happened. People of Graz think he is crazy and her parents adopted a resigned attitude toward him. She hopes to harmonize reality and the ideal in his character. She calls him a genius.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00027; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Relates Aunt Mili's thoughts that Else should have worked for a few more years as a factory inspector before getting married. Otto [Gross] her loved one, seems to be not well liked. Frieda states that every human being can fullfill their potential in association with another person.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00028; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    This is a response to Else's engagement. Frieda hopes this will not change anything in her close relationship with Else. Frieda writes about her intense love for Otto [Gross] and her happiness, but she also states he is not very supportive. The social relationships that Frieda feels obligated to are called lies by Otto. Only Frieda's father and her uncle Lusso seem to be accepting of her relationship with Otto.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1902; MS008.001.001.00029; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda states she found a home in her love to Otto [Gross], points out the parallels in her and Else's life. She talks about a previous love to Hickson, whom she feared at times. She describes Otto's ideas about love and the true woman and refers to him as a genius who is often misunderstood. However there is a terrible aspect to his life-the morphine addiction-which he tried to overcome in a rehabilitation program. She thinks this will improve when they are married.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1903; MS008.001.001.00030; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda reflects about her upcoming wedding to Otto Gross on February 23. She and Otto consider it a sacrifice to the conventions of society and to the relatives. She is looking forward to her new life with Otto. She calls it home. They will live in Otto's parents' vacation villa. Their reading list for the honeymoon is "Zarathustra, Riehl's Philosophy of the present times, a volume of Psychiatry".
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1903; MS008.001.001.00031; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda reflects on the happy times she spent with Else in her youth. Compares Else to the men in her life, who were not as important. Tells about her daily life with Otto Gross who is an assistant at the clinic. Calls him her reason for being, her great love, but she states that he acts like an ill mannered boy occasionally.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1904; MS008.001.001.00032; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda talks about the details of her planned visit to Else.
  - --- TO Anna von Richthofen, 1905; MS008.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
    Postcard - Handwriting is in an archaic German.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1906; MS008.001.001.00034; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda Gross is lonely while Otto Gross is travelling in Macedonia. She tries to figure out how a visit with Else can be arranged.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1906; MS008.001.001.00035; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda is reminiscing about her youth. She talks about the intense feeling of love and admiration she had for Else. She tells about Otto's unhappiness due to lack of intellectual stimulation, lack of friends in Graz. Otto finally received the position of assistant professor. He is disappointed about the long wait. Frieda feels guilty about her obsessive concern for her father and fears neglecting Otto. She enjoys discussing psychology with Otto.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.001.00036; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda states that she is happy about the happiness [the sexual affair] Otto is experiencing with Else. This won't affect her own love to Else whom she probably loves more than any man. She refers to Otto as "our boy." The worries about him are exhausting for her and the separation from him is a welcome break. She tells about money problems. She wants Otto's old suit for Erich Muhsam. [This letter is possibly a fragment.]
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.001.00037; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda agreed to a pact with Otto that gives him absolute freedom. She seems disappointed, resigned, and bitter about her relationship with Otto. She considered the idea of drowning herself but refrained from it because of her child Peterle. Otto displays psychotic behaviour. He doesn't change his clothes for days, doesn't wash himself until he is "healed" from what he calls "Freudian symptoms." Frieda tries not to get emotionally involved. Otto spends most of his time with Muhsam, Frank, and Benz [Sophie?].
  - --- TO Elisabeth Jaffe [Else von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.001.00038 (Box 1)
    This is only an empty envelope.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.001.00039; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda relates instructions regarding corrections for a book to be published at Vogel in Leipzig. This message is for Otto who seems to be staying with Else. She mentions Otto's presentation in Amsterdam about "secondary functions." [Letter is a fragment.]
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Else [Else von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.001.00040; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda tells about the shock and sadness she felt about "their affair." [This might refer to Else's and Otto's relationship.] She talks about the pain it causes her to see Else's affiliation with a person who hates Otto [possibly Max Weber]. She talks about an upcoming convention in Amsterdam she plans to attend with Otto. She expresses her gratitude to Else for personal favors, especially caring for Peterle, her son.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Else [Else von Richthofen], 1908; MS008.001.001.00041; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda discusses Peterle's (her infant son) care at Else's home [during the time Frieda plans to travel with Otto to Amsterdam]. She reports that Otto is trying to quit his morphine addiction. She talks about loneliness and refers to her infant son as her only friend in life. States her mission in life is to spread good will.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1908; MS008.001.001.00042; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda seems in a resigned mood because she lost the child she expected. She is not doing well physically either. She wants another child with Ernst with whom she shares an "unfortunate" love. Compares the two men Otto and Ernst, who made her life equally difficult. Called Otto's character corrupted by drugs and describes Ernst as sad, suffering, and idealistic. Otto and Ernst are working together at the Adriatic Coast and Freida fears it will end badly. Frieda reiterates her affection for Else and tries to view the future positively. Calls a woman named Lang a hysterical cow.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], 1909; MS008.001.001.00043; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Fragment. Frieda asks existential question about her life and expresses fear about her own and her boys' future. Sofie is expecting a child which Otto acknowledges as his own. Frieda mentions she is spending 70 Marks for Sofie to have the child. She feels guilty about the hysteria that surrounds the child and calls the situation disgusting. Frieda mentions Adele's statement after Peter's birth, that they would emigrate to America if "such a thing" would happen again. [Letter is a fragment and has two ink spots.]
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to "Love of my heart" [Else von Richthofen], 1909; MS008.001.001.00044; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Frieda states how much Else is in her thoughts. She is like the everlasting light in an environment which she calls mostly gloomy. She refers to the fragile state of her own health. She enoys her English courses at the university. In general she is disappointed in herself and what she achieved in life.
  - [Frieda Gross-Schloffer] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00045; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Fragment of a letter. Subjects: her relationship with probably Otto Gross; discusses her individuals, special status in his life, in contrast to other women in his life.Compares her children, Eva-Verena and Peter.
  - [Frieda Gross] Friedel to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00046; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subjects: Relationship with Ernst [probably Frick] She has a resigned attitude toward him. She describes her children Eva Verena, the baby, whose father is Ernst [Frick] and Peter [Father Otto Gross] who has significant mood changes. Her father dies in Graz.
  - [Frieda Gross] Friedel to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00047; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subjects: Fredel is upset about suicide notice of Sofie [Benz] (out of newspaper). Questions the extent of responsibility of Otto Gross' involvement in death. Comments on Sofie's and Otto's personalities, which both share mental illness. Ernst [Frick] is angry about the incident with Sofie and Otto-- Fredel pities Otto, but is disdainful of him.
  - Friedel [Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00048; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Describes relationship with Ernst [Frick] whom she calls sick. She is disillusioned and resigned about this relationship. She met with Otto [Gross] during his drug rehabilitation and is very pessimistic about him returning to his old addictive pattern soon. She talks about her own daily struggle with life.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00049; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Reaction to an illness of Else's and description of the strong friendship between them. Fredel's hunger for love. Fredel is pregnant again...her life is quite restless; she hopes this child [of Ernst Frick's] will help her relationship with Ernst, unhappy Love. Another visit of Fredel's with Otto, whom she describes as strangely healthy, yet unbearable. He wants to see her again. Request for money for Ernst's trip to England.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00050; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Letter is a fragment; she asks Else for 3000 mark but does not want to disclose the purpose of the loan.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00051; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Letter is a fragment; After receiving money from Else... Fredel has lost her unborn child, she thanks Else [Bethel] for her support during this tough time. She discloses that Ernst has left her for England to be with Friedele and claims not to be jealous. sentimental and melancholic mood.
  - Friedel [Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00052; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: She is talking about vacation plans with Frick to visit Lake Geneva.
  - Ernst Frick to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00053; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)